Grex Staff Notes: About Grex's Hardware and Software

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

NOTE: These notes are of historical value only!

Please note that Grex has changed drastically since these notes were written. In particular, it is no longer running on Sun hardware, nor is it running SunOS. As of mid-2017, Grex is an x86 machine based machine a modern BSD. Much of the software listed below is installed, but much more recent versions, and most of it through the OS ports collection. Notable exceptions are things written by people close to Grex itself, such as the Backtalk conferencing software.

[index]

This note describes briefly the hardware and software used on Grex. Cyberspace Communications has very little money to spend, and we have a very large number of users on our systems, so, although we don't have much, we work it very hard.

Hardware

The inventory database gives a bare-bones list of all the equipment we owned by Grex. This document describes the systems and their configurations in more detail.

Main Grex Computer

Our main computer is currently a Sun SPARCserver 4/670MP. This is a pretty decent machine by our standards. We actually bought our first 4/670 system and had it running at least a year before it got fashionable for companies to stop using them and start pushing them off their loading docks. Lately though, we've been lucky enough to catch a few that were being dumped.

Sun's SPARC machines are all RISC (Reduced Instruction Set Computer) architectures. This is sort of the opposite approach to chip design from things like Intel's Pentium chips. The basic idea behind RISC is to start with a very simple processor that handles a small, orthogonal instruction set, and then work like heck to make it do the simple things it does very fast. There are several RISC architectures around, but Sun's SPARC architecture is probably the most commercially successful.

Grex's actual 4/670 system consists of the following components:

1 | Sun | 12-slot chassis with power supply and fans.
1 | Sun 501-1439 | backplane with 12 VME card connectors.
1 | Sun 501-1686
(Rev 06) | 4/6xx VME motherboard with boot proms (version 2.10), two Mbus connectors, three SBus connectors, a SCSI controller, an ethernet interface, two serial ports and 32 sockets for 30-pin SIMMs.
1 | Sun 501-1901
(Rev 06) | 4/6xx VME memory expansion card with 64 sockets for 30-pin SIMMs.
2 | Sun 370-1388 | SM100 Mbus module with two 40MHz Ross CPUs.
1 | Performance Technologies PT-SBS430 | S-Bus SCSI Controller Daughterboard
96 | Various | 4-Meg (80ns) SIMMs (30-pin).
2 | HP 3010 | 2.1 Gig Full Height SCSI Disks.
3 | Seagate ST42400N | 2.1 Gig Full Height SCSI Disks.
2 | Seagate ST15150N | 4.1 Gig Full Height SCSI Disks.
1 | Toshiba XM3401B | CD-ROM Drive.
1 | Exabyte Mammoth | 8mm Tape Drive.

We are currently running on a two SM100 modules, so it is a four processor system. We will probably experiment with removing one module, giving us just two processors, because we aren't convinced that the system wouldn't be faster that way. This is because of the limitations of SunOS 4.1.4, which we will discuss more below.

Our motherboard is fully populated with 32 4-Meg SIMMs, and there are 64 more in the memory expansion board, so Grex has 384 Megs of total memory. (You could put in 16-Meg SIMMs instead, which is actually more cost effective on a dollars per megabyte basis, but we didn't have the money for them.) Unfortunately 30-pin SIMMS are no longer made, and are thus a bit scarce, so the cost on these isn't coming down as much as other memory.

The 4/670 was designed around 1991 as an enterprise server machine, one that will be simultaneously used by many users. It is solidly over-engineered for robustness and stability. This is in contrast to most Intel systems which are designed primarily to work as single-user desktop workstations and are built as cheaply as humanly possible. The difference is not so much in the speed of the processor (probably most modern Pentium systems easily could outrun the 4/670 at a single task), but in hardware features that make it better able to juggle many tasks. For example, Sun's servers have "hardware contexts" where the states of many different running jobs can be stored in the processor, so that the processor can jump almost instantaneously between them. Pentium systems have only one hardware context - whatever is being run at the moment. Our previous computer, a Sun 4/260, had 16 hardware contexts. The Sun 4/670 (with the SM100 processors that we have) supports 4,096 hardware contexts in each processor. Features like this mean that the 4/670 can deliver a lot better performance in our application than you'd expect from four 40 MHz processors.

We purchased this machine piecemeal, with money donated by our users in a fundraiser. Since then, many spare parts and add-on have been donated by various people. In January of 1997, we bought a second-hand Sun 4/370 from the University of Michigan property disposition for $212. We used only the chassis, backplane and power supply from this for the new system. A chassis is expensive to ship, so buying it locally was advantagous. In Februrary of 1997, we purchased a second-hand 4/600MP board and a memory board from CRA, Inc for $718, an SM100 module from Piece by Piece for $40 (plus $10 shipping) and 20 (two spares) 4-Meg memory chips from QuickerCAD and Ken Olsen for $440. In December of 1997 we bought 16 additional SIMMs for $248. Thus the total cost of the machine, not including disk drives, was $1718. The CD-ROM was donated to Grex by Tod Plesco.

In January of 1999, two different donors gave us parts of two different Sun 4/690 systems. A 4/690 is exactly like a 4/670, but in a different box. It comes in a rack mount chassis that uses 220-volt power instead of 110-volt. One donor gave us a spare motherboard, a rack, a VME card bay, and a drive bay. The other donor gave us a motherboard, three more SM100 processor boards, 32 4-Meg SIMMs, 10 2.1 Gig differential SCSI drives, plus another rack-mount drive bay, and various SBus cards. A pair of processors and 16 memory chips were added. Then in February we were about to collect another 16 4-Meg SIMMs from a number of different donors, and brought Grex up to 256M of memory. Since then, as the 4/670 continues it's slide toward total obsolesence, more and more components have been appearing on our doorstep. In July 2001, we added the SBus SCSI controller, so that a second SCSI chain could be supported. We are building a second 4/670 for use as a backup and development system.

Routers

Grex is currently connected to the internet by a 144K DSL connection. The router is FlowPoint/2200-12 SDSL Router. Very conventional and even vaguely modern.

Before we had DSL, we had a 128K ISDN link and a pair of Pipeline P50s. Before we had the ISDN link, Grex was connected to the internet through a 28K dial-up PPP connection. Our router at that time was a machine called "Gryps." It started as a 386 system running FreeBSD, then got upgraded to a 100 MHz Pentium running OpenBSD. It still serves a few functions, like supporting the terminal servers, and acting as a gateway machine for staff.

Modems and Terminal Server

Grex maintains 7 of its own dial-in modems. The number has been steadily decreasing as more and more of our users change over to using the net connection instead of dialing direct. All are 14.4 GVC modems that look identical, but since they were bought at two different dates, they have two different chipsets in them. All modems connect to a Chase IOLan terminal server called "groupie", which interfaces up to 16 modems to our local ethernet. It is configured to be transparent, so that dial-in users are automatically given telnet connections to Grex, without going through any kind of menu. We have a spare Chase IOLan called "groovy" which is not currently being used. Groupie and Groovy were donated to Grex by Rob Argy.

System Software

Operating System

Grex runs SunOS version 4.1.4. Sun has changed over to a new operating system called Solaris 2 (and retroactively renamed SunOS 4.1.4 to Solaris 1.1.2), and is rumored to be close to ending their support of SunOS 4. At the time that we were setting up Grex, Solaris 2 had a somewhat poor reputation among computer gurus - it was generally thought to run slower and less reliably then SunOS 4 did. Since we had a very heavily loaded machine, we felt that we couldn't afford the slower speed or lower reliability, and thus choose SunOS. (Actually, since we were on a Sun 2 at the time, I suspect Solaris wasn't even available.)

At this point Solaris has probably improved enough so that it would be possible to change over to using it, but changing over from SunOS to Solaris is a very big job. We've made many modifications to our system, including modifications to the kernel, and converting them over to a new operating system would be difficult.

As it is, SunOS 4.1.4 has worked very well for us. We've been placing our machines under extremely high loads for many years, and the robustness and performance of the system have been genuinely impressive (though to the casual user who doesn't appreciate the capacity of the hardware and the size of the load it has sometimes seemed impressively pathetic). Much as we'd like to have access to source code for the operating system, we feel that none of the free Unix versions currently available would perform as well under these conditions as SunOS.

Sun still regularly releases new patches for SunOS 4.1.4. We regularly check the current patch report and try to keep Grex current. A list of installed patches is in the /etc/patchlist file.

Unfortunately, SunOS 4.1.4 wasn't really designed to work with multiprocessor systems like the Sun 4/670. Many kernel functions depend on the assumption that only one processor is executing them at a time. To make SunOS 4.1.4 work at all on multiprocessor systems, Sun took a drastic approach - they allow only one processor in the kernel at a time. This is simple, but it has a big performance penalty. If one user's process has done a kernel call to read a file from the disk, and another user's process wants to call the kernel to send a packet out on the net, then the second process must wait for the first one to get out of the kernel. This is obnoxious. On Grex most processes spend almost 50% of their time in the kernel, so if you have two processors and the system is fully loaded, then there is a processor in the kernel almost 100% of the time. If we added any more processors, they would probably spend most of their time waiting around, and, since interprocessor communication isn't done all that efficiently under SunOS 4.1.4, it's quite possible that adding more processors to communicate between would actually slow the system down. These problems are fixed in Solaris, which has a true multi-threaded kernel so processors spend much less time waiting for each other.

The Sun 4/670 appears to be the last machine Sun made which could run SunOS 4.1.4 at all. So if Grex ever wants to move to a more powerful machine, we will have to move away from SunOS. However, we are currently thinking that the future of Grex lies not in building faster and faster machines, but in going to a distributed system consisting of multiple machines.

Kernel Modifications - Internet Blocks

Most Unix system administrators are very interested in keeping strangers off of their computers, but have no problem letting users of their machines access the internet. At Grex, our requirements are different. We let anyone at all onto our computer, but since we don't want it used as just a stepping stone for people who want to attack other servers on the net, we limit the ways in which people can connect to the net from our machine.

To enforce this, we have made some modifications to our SunOS kernel that prevent most users from making most kinds of outbound internet connections from our host. The kernel of a Unix operating system is the part that schedules all processes and organizes and controls access to all devices (disk, memory, CPU, ethernet, serial ports, etc), so putting these blocks there means that they cannot be bypassed. For detailed information on how this works, see the kernel blocks page.

Kernel Modifications - Fork Killer

We also have occasional problems with users running fork bombs on Grex. A fork bomb is simple a program that endlessly launches copies of itself, each of which also endlessly launches copies of itself. Fork bombs can slow the system down badly, and can be hard to kill because new processes are created faster than anyone can type kill commands.

SunOS has the ability to limit the maximum number of simultaneous processes any one user can have running. Setting this limit to a low number (32 processes on Grex) reduces the annoyance of fork bombs, but doesn't eliminate it. So we modified the kernel so that if any user tries to use more than 32 processes then that user is instantly logged out and all his processes killed. We also modified the kernel's kill logic so that processes can be killed while they are forking. This pretty much eliminates all problems with fork bombs.

Free Software

There is a huge amount of public domain or Gnu-license software available for Unix systems, and a lot of it is installed on Grex. The Gnu project especially is steadily working away at creating a complete free Unix system. They have developed very good versions of most of the Unix utilities, and these are widely used by all the free Unix versions (Linux, FreeBSD, etc). We have installed most of these in the /usr/local/bin directory on Grex, so that most of the commands you'll find there are actually Gnu versions rather than SunOS versions, though the Sun versions are still available.

The following is an incomplete (and probably soon to be obsolete) list of the freely distributed software installed on Grex:

Program | Version | Description
apache | 1.3.26 | Apache HTTP Server Daemon
bash | 2.05 | Gnu Borne-Again Shell (enhanced sh shell)
bison | 1.25 | Gnu Yacc clone (yet another compiler compiler)
cvs | 1.10 | Gnu Concurrent Versions System
diffutils | 2.7 | Gnu File Comparison Tools
elm | 2.5.2 | Elm Electronic Mail Program
emacs | 20.3 | Gnu Emacs Text Editor
fileutils | 3.16 | Gnu File Utilities (ls, chmod, mv, rm, etc)
findutils | 4.1 | Gnu Find Utility
gawk | 3.0.3 | Gnu Awk
gcc | 2.95.3 | Gnu Compiler Collection (C, C++, Fortran 77, Objective C, CHILL, but not Java)
gdb | 5.0 | Gnu Debugger
grep | 2.4.2 | Gnu Grep
gzip | 1.2.4 | Gnu File Compresser
ispell | 3.2.04 | Gnu International Spell Checker
joe | 2.8 | Joe's Own Editor
less | 332 | Gnu Pager
libg++ | 2.7.2 | Gnu C++ Library
lynx | 2.8.4 | Text Based Web Browser
make | 3.76.1 | Gnu Make Program
msql | 2.0.3 | Hughes Technologies Mini SQL
mysql | 3.23.39 | mySQL SQL
ncurses | 5.2 | New Curses screen management package
nethack | 3.3.0 | Net-Created Dungeon Game
openssl | 0.9.6b | Secure Sockets Layer Toolkit
patch | 2.5 | Gnu Patch Program
perl | 5.004_004 | Perl Interpreter
pine | 3.96 | Pine Mailer
procmail | 3.10 | Mail Processor
screen | 3.7.4 | Gnu Screen Manager
sh-utils | 1.16 | Gnu Shell Utilities (date, echo, who, stty, etc)
ssh | 1.2.20 | Secure Shell Remote Login Program
tar | 1.12 | Gnu Tape Archiver
tcl | 8.3.3 | Tcl Programming language
tcsh | 6.10.00 | Extended C Shell
texinfo | 3.9 | Gnu Documentation System
textutils | 1.22 | Gnu Text Utilities (cat, head, wc, sum, etc)
top | 3.5beta7 | Top CPU Usage Display
vim | 5.8 | Improved VI editor
w3m | 0.1.10 | Text-based Web Browser
wget | 1.5.3 | Noninteractive Downloading Utility
zsh | 3.0.5 | Z shell

We have both the Gnu gcc compiler and the Sun C compiler, but most of our software is built with the Gnu compiler, which conforms with the ANSI standards and generally produces better code.

In a few cases we've found the Gnu versions of commands unsatisfactory. Their "df" command behaved oddly on unmounted disks, reporting partitions that didn't exist, so we pulled it out. Newer versions of their "who" command do DNS lookups on each IP address of each user. Since we have users from many different domains, and many are not resolvable, this is very slow, so we fell back to an older version of the Gnu "who" program.

Password Database

SunOS 4.1.4 uses a flat password file with encrypted passwords stored in the publicly readable file. This is totally inadequate for our needs. With over 28,000 lines in the password file, searching it is much too slow. Also, since untrusted users can easily get onto our system, and password cracking technology is pretty good these days, leaving encrypted passwords in a publicly readable password file would be a very large security problem. We have installed a much-modified version of the JFH password system to give us a hashed password database for quick look-ups and a protected shadow file to keep encrypted passwords in. For more information about this, see the Grex staff notes on the password database. To support this, we have rebuilt many programs with our own shadow library, and have installed our own versions of such programs like passwd, chfn, chsh, etc.

Queuing Telnet Daemon

The vast majority of Grex users connect into the system via telnet connections. To keep the system from being too slow to use, we limit the number of simultaneous telnet sessions that can be established. Originally this was done by limiting the number of psuedo-tty devices (ptys) installed, but this approach had many problems. Telnetting into the system became a lottery: when you tried to telnet in, you either succeeded or failed. If you failed, you tried again and kept trying again until you happened to hit it when there was a psuedo-tty available. Rejecting all these repeated attempts slowed down the system, especially as users started developing "attack telnet scripts" to telnet repeatedly until a connection succeeded. People could only get on by being lucky or persistant. Furthermore, we wanted to use the terminal server for dial-in users, but dial-in users effectively telnet in from the terminal server, and we didn't have any way to reserve connections for those dial-in users. Finally, when the system is full of users, there were no psuedo-ttys left available, so programs like "screen" could not be used.

Marcus Watts largely solved these problems with the development of his queuing telnet daemon. With this, users telnetting in from the terminal server always get a connection, but users telnetting in from anywhere else must pass through the queue. If the maximum allowed number of users is already on, then additional users are placed on a queue, where they see a count-down showing their progress through the queue. Actual telnet connections are given to users as space is available, in the order that they telnetted in.

The queuing telnet daemon solves most of our telnet problems. Users can get connections in a fair and predictable fashion, "attack telnet" programs are useless, and plenty of pseudo-ttys are left available for dial-in and "screen" users. Users on the queue do still cost some processing to maintain, so having a long queue can contribute to slowing down the system.

We are also running a queuing version of the rlogin daemon. Unfortunately, there was no good way to build queuing into the ssh daemon, but we have modified it so that it can't be used as a way around the queue. This means that it mostly can't be used at all when the system is full.

For more information about the queuing telnet daemon, contact Marcus Watts.

Idle Zapper

Because telnet connections are a scarce quantity on Grex, we run an idle daemon to automatically log out users who aren't doing anything on their connections. We use Michael Crider's freeware "idled" program, with a few small modifications and bug fixes. We have set it to warn idle users after 15 minutes and then log them out if they are still idle 5 minutes later. If a user logs into Grex more than once and Grex has more than a certain number of users logged in, idled sends warnings to their oldest connections, asking the users to please log out. Some programs (including some versions of "less") like to read and write from /dev/tty instead of from the user's actual tty device. This means that activity in those programs may not be noticed by "idled". We have fixed some of those programs on Grex. Valerie Mates has been the main person responsible for maintaining the idled on Grex.

Process Monitor

Since we primarily regulate load by limiting the number of simultaneous users, we try to prevent people from leaving processes running after they log off, because otherwise you can accumulate an awful lot of running processes even if you keep the number of users low.

To enforce this, and to generally keep a watch on the process table, we run a program called "robocop". This was originally written as a shell script named "kill_orphans" by Greg Cronau, and has evolved into a much faster and more sophisticated C program written by Jan Wolter.

"Robocop" regularly scans the list of users currently logged on and the process table, and then kills any process left behind by a user who has logged off. That includes all processes which fail all the following tests:

The real user ID of the process is not one of the system accounts like "root", "daemon" or "nobody".
The control tty is not the console and does not have either someone logged into it, or a "screen" or "layer" process running on it.
The process is not a "sendmail" or "ftpd" process, nor is it a descendent of a "sendmail" or "ftpd" process.

"Robocop" also does some simple tests to try to detect users using excess resources (mainly people running fork bombs and other denial of service attacks). If a user has too many processes, or the processes are using too much memory, it automatically kills all the user's processes. This function has been partly obsoleted by the kernel modifications which kill fork bombs more quickly than robocop does.

"Robocop" also cleans up "ftpd" processes that are more than 6 hours old. These are often left behind when people's ftp connections are broken, and we don't want them cluttering up the process table forever.

In all its tasks, "robocop" is designed to err on the side of not killing processes that might be OK, so it is not by any means impossible to fool. However, Grex staff monitor things pretty closely, so what "robocop" misses is usually cleaned up by a human pretty fast.

Note also that "robocop" is very tuned toward Grex and SunOS 4.1. Porting it to another system would be non-trivial.

Hierarchical Home Directories

On most Unix systems, all users are given home directories under a single parent directory. Typically, the home directory for user "bubbles" would be someplace like "/home/bubbles." But Grex has over 28,000 users, so our "/home" directory would have more than 28,000 entries in it. Any time anyone accesses their home directory by its full path, the operating system would have to search the 28,000 entry parent directory. On average, it would have to look through 14,000 directory entries. This is seriously slow.

We have restructured our home directories into a two level hierarchy. Instead of the directory for "bubbles" being "/a/bubbles" it is now "/a/b/u/bubbles", where "b" and "u" are the first and second letters of the user's login name respectively. This way the operating system has to search the top level directory (with 26 entries), the second-level directory (another 26 directories) and the the third-level directory (with an average of 28,000/(26*26) = 41 directories). On average it should have to look at about 47 directory entries (that is 26/2 + 26/2 + 41/2), which is a big improvement on 14,000. For further optimization, we carefully created the intermediate directories for the most common letters first, so that the average search times are actually even lower than the estimate above.

Some users' accounts are now being created on the new /c disk instead of /a. These users have home directories like /c/b/u/bubbles instead.

Hierarchical Mail Directories

Unix normally stores the unread mail for all users in a single directory, such as /var/spool/mail. On Grex roughly two-thirds of our users have mail files in that directory, so this was another huge directory that needs to be searched every time a piece of mail was delivered or a mail reader was started. So, as another trick to speed up the system, we set up the same two-level directory hierarchy on the mail spool directory as we set up for users' home directories.

Making this work required modifications to our "mail.local" program, to make it deliver to the correct place ("mail.local" is the program that "sendmail" invokes to do local mail delivery). The configuration file /etc/mailfmt tells where mail should be delivered by "mail.local".

Modifications were also made to the "login" program to correctly set the MAIL environment variable to the location of the user's mail file, and to all the mail reading programs that did not respect the MAIL environment variable (notably "pine").

Mailbox Directory Permissions

On standard SunOS systems, the /var/spool/mail directory is permitted 2777, which allows anyone to create or delete their own mailboxes, but not to delete other people's mailboxes. Unfortunately, it's also possible for vandals to create someone else's mailbox, which gives you access to their mail. So when we switched to heirarchical mail directories we also changed the directory permissions to 755 - so people can't create or delete their own mailboxes, though they can empty them. Mailboxes are created by "mail.local" and we don't delete them until the account is deleted. Changes were also made to the kind of locking used when reading or writing mailboxes (flock is now used).

This was a problem for some mail programs. Sun's "Mail" mail reader bombs if it can't delete mail files. Since we didn't have source to it, Marcus Watts extended "mailx" to give it the same features as "Mail" and we now use that instead. If you run "pine" before you have ever received mail, it complains that you haven't got a mail box and that it can't create one. This is harmless, but the message confuses some users. Someday we need to kill this error message, but figuring out "pine" source is amazingly painful. We have modified the error message to be less alarming.

Mailbox Size Quotas

Grex has had problems with users who take out an account, sign up for high traffic mailing lists, and then never log in again. Huge quantities of mail pile up, jamming our net connection as it comes in and filling our mail spool partition once it is here. Once the mail partition is full, nobody can receive mail. Similar problems are caused by people mailing in huge files, often gif images or executable programs.

To limit these problems, Grex has set limits on mail. Messages that are longer than 600K are refused so that they bounce back to the sender. If a user's mailbox grows larger than one megabyte, then we bounce all new messages for that user in a similar manner.

This was implemented by Marcus Watts. The "mail.local" program which does local mail delivery detects when a mailbox is too full, and adds that user's login name to the file /var/adm/badmail. "Sendmail" was taught to reject all mail to people who are listed in that file. A new program called "umailck" deletes users from the badmail file if they are no longer over quota. It is run hourly by "cron". "Login" warns users if they are near or over quota, and runs "umailck" on them if they are in the /var/adm/badmail file.

Marcus's original idea was that we would reject mail sent to accounts which were overquota with a "temporary" error. This tells the machine sending the mail to Grex to try again later, by which time the user might have emptied out the mailbox enough so that the message could be delivered. This was nice in theory because this way no mail would be lost. In practice we discovered that some mail hosts try again immediately so Grex would end up rejecting the same mail message many times a minute. We couldn't afford this, so we changed it to reject over-quota mail with a "permanent" error, so it would be bounced immediately to the sender.

Spam Filters

"Spammers" are people who send huge amounts of unsolicited E-mail to tens of thousands of people, usually advertising various forms of worthless garbage. Spamming is an attractive way to advertise because you can reach a lot of people very cheaply. However, most people don't like receiving this kind of mail, so in the early days it was common for people who had received unwanted spam to apply poetic justice by sending back thousands of E-mail messages in reply, thus flooding the spammer's systems with junk E-mail.

Because of this, modern spammers try very hard to send their E-mail in such a way that nobody can reply to it, or otherwise easily trace it back to them. They use forged return addresses, so that replies go to the wrong place, or they relay their messages through machines belonging to other people, thus using some unknowing person's machine to send out their spam.

We at Grex, like many other people on the net, are philosophically opposed to people doing nefarious things so they can send E-mail without being held accountable for it, and we are even more strongly opposed to letting people use our already overburdened machine for this purpose. Like many other systems on the net, we've been steadily instituting new measures to try to block spam mail while still passing through legitimate mail. Meanwhile, of course, spammers have been steadily inventing new ways around the new defenses.

Recent versions of "sendmail " contain many new features designed to limit spam. Unfortunately, we've made so many modifications to our "sendmail" for various other purposes that upgrading to the newest version is rather difficult. So Grex staff member Marcus Watts has been waging his own war against spam, monitoring the spam that passes through the system, building defenses against common spammer tricks into our version of "sendmail", and blocking all mail from sites that regularly seem to be originating spam.

Un-POP Server

Grex doesn't run a POP server. Providing mail service to the universe is not our primary goal, even if it is much of what we end up doing. We want people to get involved in our virtual community, so we want them actually get on the system to get their mail.

But lots of people try accessing their mail via a POP client and then send us mail asking why it doesn't work. So we set up a fake POP server that simply rejects all POP connections with an error message that explains that Grex does not support POP. This little program was written for Grex by Jared Mauch.

Disk Space Quotas

Grex policy sets a limit on 1 megabyte of disk space per user. SunOS 4.1.4 contains software to enforce such quotas, but we do not use it here. It would slow down the system considerably to have to be constantly checking quotas. Instead we police disk usage manually.

Application Software

Newuser Program

The "newuser" program creates new accounts for people. Grex runs two versions of this. The one that you run by telnetting or dialing Grex and typing "newuser" at the login prompt was originally written by Marcus Watts for M-Net in 1983, and has been slowly and steadily evolving ever since. The web-based one that you run by pointing your browser at www.grex.org/newuser/ is a new interface to Marcus's same old account creation code, that was developed by Jan Wolter. More than two hundred people run one or the other newuser program on Grex every day.

PicoSpan Conferencing System

Grex's main reason for existing is to host a virtual community, based primarily on the PicoSpan conferencing system. We have over 100 active conferences on Grex, with a wide range of subject areas. The PicoSpan program, which is accessed by the Unix "bbs" command, allows user to join any of these conferences (except the "staff" conference which is restricted to Grex's staff members and used only for technical discussions and coordination of efforts among staff). Users can read, post new responses to existing discussion items, or start new items. It keeps track of what you have read in files saved in your home directory and called "participation files", so you only see new material when you come by again.

PicoSpan was written by grex staff member Marcus Watts around 1983. It is the same conferencing system made famous on "The Well".

Backtalk Conferencing System

More recently Grex staff members Jan Wolter and Steve Weiss have developed the web-based Backtalk conferencing system. On Grex, Backtalk is set up to access the same conferences as PicoSpan and use the same participation files, so that it doesn't really matter which interface you use, or if you mix and match them. Backtalk is available free to other systems.

Users log into Backtalk using their usual Grex logins and passwords. This is a bit tricky, because neither Backtalk nor the httpd run as root and the encrypted passwords are stored in the shadow file which is readable only by root. To get around this, we have the http daemon run an external authentication module called "pwauth". Since this does run as root, it can check passwords. This authentication system is available for free.

Party Program

Grex's party program is real-time chat program where you can hold live conversations with whatever other users are currently running it. It's vaguely like IRC, except it only has Grex users on it and there are no "channel operators". Party was originally written by Marcus Watts around 1983. Jan Wolter started modifying it around 1985, and eventually completely rewrote it, adding many features.

Orville Write Program

Orville Write is a much extended version of the Unix write program written by Jan Wolter. Among other things, it supports the sending of "telegrams" between users, and allows users to designate themselves as "helpers". Doing "write help" connects you to any available user who has designated themselves as a "helper."

Vote Program

Grex is run democratically, with members electing board members, and voting on referenda. Since we run lots of elections, we need a vote program. Ours was written by Grex staff member John Remmers. It has both a command-line interface and a web interface.

Menu Shell

Since Unix commands are often difficult for new users to learn, Dave Parks developed a menu system for M-Net long ago. This system is designed to give users an easy interface to commonly used Unix commands, and also to teach the users what those commands are, so that one day they will be able to switch from menu shell to a more standard Unix shell. Grex's menu shell was a version of Dave Parks's menu shell, installed on Grex by Dave Parks and modified by Valerie Mates in the years since.

The whole thing was implemented as one giant sh script. We weren't entirely happy with the maintainability and efficiency of this implementation.

Michelangelo Giansiracusa re-wrote the shell scripts into a C program template design, which means configuring menu templates is easy and can be done by some menu-admin person who is programming-illiterate. Some new features, back-end scripts, and improved help messages were also added to the newmenu system in this project undertaken by Mic. A template format debugger program was also written by Mic, which may be more helpful to Grex users if we someday decide they can construct their own customizable menu template files.

Most of our users are not any kind of Unix gurus, and being able to offer an interface that is more approachable for novice users is important.

Lynx Shell

Grex staffers Steve Weiss, Rob Henderson, and Carl Miller have also developed a shell based on the lynx that gives a more hypertext-flavored menu interface. This is a good concept, but Steve says it probably needs more work.

Help System

When you type "help" at a shell prompt on Grex, this runs Grex's help system. The help system is an archive of various files of Grex documentation. You can also go from the help system into either of Grex's menu systems, or you can request a chat with a volunteer helper. Valerie Mates wrote and maintains the help system; it is a shell script.

The Change Program

When you type change at a shell prompt, or select "Change password, etc" from a menu, this runs Grex's Change program. This program is a user friendly collection of shell scripts, awk programs, Perl programs, and C code that users can use to change settings on their accounts without needing to memorize cryptic acronyms like chfn (change full name), or needing to know that if you switch to a shell that uses different startup files than your current shell then you must also create the startup files for your new shell or your account will be broken. The change program was written and is maintained by Valerie Mates.

Document History:

Apr 4, 1998: Jan Wolter (janc) - Initial revision.
Apr 10, 1998: Valerie Mates (valerie) - Added sections about the help and change programs; split the section about the menu programs into two sections and expanded each section; many minor corrections and tweaks.
Jun 19, 1998: Jan Wolter (janc) - Minor updates. Deleted "DRAFT" disclaimor.
Feb 4, 1999: Jan Wolter (janc) - Replace section about "kill_orphans" with section about "robocop".
Feb 11, 1999: Jan Wolter (janc) - Update description of 4/670 to reflect donated parts.
Feb 18, 1999: Jan Wolter (janc) - Added short section on kernel blocks.
Mar 25, 1999: Jan Wolter (janc) - Updated robocop info, added Orville Write info.
Sep 19, 1999: Jan Wolter (janc) - Added info about fork killer kernel modifiations.
Oct 1, 1999: Jan Wolter (janc) - Expanded and corrected info on mail directories and quotas.
Jul 7, 2000: Michelangelo Giansiracusa (spooked) - Added note on re-design of menu system.
May 28, 2001: Jan Wolter (janc) - General update of hardware information.
Jul 16, 2001: Jan Wolter (janc) - More updates of hardware information.
Jul 20, 2008: Dan Cross (cross) - Convert to XHTML and deprecate.

$Id: about.xhtml 1607 2017-05-31 16:16:21Z cross $ We welcome your feedback.

NOTE: These notes are of historical value only!

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

Grex has changed radically since this note was first written. It no longer runs on a Sun running SunOS, but rather on an x86 machine running an open source BSD-based operating system. However, IRC bots (or bots of any kind) are still not allowed on Grex. Though we have much better network connectivity now, we do not want to upset our network provider or colocation service with malicious activity originating from Grex, so we severely limit what services users can run on Grex itself. Sorry, eggdrop and other bots are still not allowed.

[index]

Grex Staff Notes: Frequently Asked Questions about Eggdrop and other Programs not Welcome on Grex

We have had thousands of users asking about running IRC bots, IRC clients, and bouncers on our system. We are sorry to say that we do not and can not support eggdrop or any other IRC bot or bouncer here on Grex. We do allow IRC clients to be run, but only by paying users, not for free. Since lots of people seem to be confused and irate about this, we thought we'd write a bit more about this policy.

What are IRC Clients?

IRC is the "Internet Relay Chat," a huge Internet-wide live chat area. You can create "channels" on IRC where you can talk to other people who also join the channel. Every line you type is seen by all the other people in the channel, and you see every line they type. To connect to the IRC, you need an IRC client, just like you need a web browser to read the web. If your computer has a web connection, you can run one there. Or you can connect to another computer, either over the net or by dialing in, and run an IRC client there to connect to the IRC.

Grex does not give non-paying users access to the IRC. Grex has the "irc 2.8.2" client installed for the use of our members. There are others that could be installed if our members wanted, like BitchX or mIRC, but there has been no demand for them. Occasionally people trying to get around this restriction try to download and install their own copies of IRC clients. This doesn't work. See below.

What is Eggdrop?

Eggdrop is the most popular of many so-called "IRC-bots". There is quite a bit of good information about eggdrop on the web. We obviously aren't eggdrop experts, so if you really want to know a lot about it, you may want to search elsewhere for info.

Eggdrop is used with IRC. Computer programs can be written that join IRC channels just like a human would through an IRC client. Such programs, called "bots" or "robots," can interact with people in various ways. Besides being cute, bots can perform some useful functions, like holding channels open when nobody is home, keeping them from being taken over by other users, controlling what users can join the channel, providing extra lag-free talk channels that aren't affected by net-splits, allowing users to upload and download files, and linking between different IRC networks. Lots of people who want to rule their own channels want eggdrop bots. It's a useful and valuable tool.

Eggdrop needs to run on a Unix system, which isn't hard to find (several excellent free Unix systems exist that can be installed on most any PC). However, to gain the full benefit of eggdrop, you need to be running it on a system that is connected to the internet 24 hours a day, which isn't true for most people's home computers. So lots of people are looking for systems to run eggdrop on, and lots of people come looking here at Grex. After lots of hard work, they eventually discover that eggdrop won't work here. See below.

What are Bouncers?

Some people would like to be able to connect to IRC without revealing their identities. One way to do this would be to install a small program on a system like Grex which just bounces their IRC connection. Then they point the IRC client on their computer to the bouncer running on Grex, which reflects the connection to an IRC server someplace else. Then it looks to everyone on the IRC as if the connection is coming from Grex, not from this person's own computer. You can even get fancier, and chain together several bouncers, so your connection goes through several places before hitting your destination, making it even harder to trace. And this doesn't only work for IRC, it works for almost any kind of net connection.

The most common bouncer is called bnc or boun or bounce. There seem to be several others, including datapipe and anonirc.

Since Grex accounts can be obtained without giving much (or any) personal information, lots of people think Grex is a pretty good place to put a bouncer. We currently have about half a dozen different people try to install one every day. None of them work. See below.

What is Grex?

Grex is a public access system supported entirely by donations from its users. We have no corporate or government funding. Although we have about 25,000 users, only around 100 of them ever give us any money and most of them don't give us much. All the staff work to maintain this system is done by unpaid volunteers who do work here only because they enjoy using this system and believe in our system's mission. We are not wealthy, and our computer is not one any sane person would be proud to own (you can take a look at it here).

What is this mission that inspires people to donate money to us and do work for us?

First, we house a virtual community of users who come here to talk to each other - to learn, to teach, to flirt, to laugh, to share their ideas and opinions. Almost all of our support comes from people who take part in that on-line community and feel that it is an important enough part of their lives that they want to help support it.
Second, we have a charitable mission: to provide free net access to people who can not justify the expense of a commercial internet account. We believe that it is important that all people have access to the net, regardless of economic status. Because there are many such people needing access and because we have very limited resources, we can provide only the most basic services:

We have a very good conferencing area, open to all.
We have our own live chat area, open to all.
We provide free Email, but not POP or mailing lists.
We provide access to a non-graphical web browser.
We provide free web pages space, but can't allow graphics.
We provide full shell access for those interested in learning Unix.
For members, we support IRC, but not IRC bots.
We provide incoming telnet and ftp service, but limit outgoing service to members.

We'd love to be able to provide more free services, but given how few resources we have, it's a miracle that we can do as much as we do. We have to set some limits on services.

Why doesn't Grex provide free IRC access?

Our impression is that, second only to E-mail, IRC is the free service most in demand on the net. We sometimes still question whether offering E-mail was all that bright an idea. What we really want to do is conferencing, but providing free E-mail consumes vastly more of our computer resources and staff time than conferencing does. But it really does seem to be a very worthwhile service for an awful lot of people, so we're willing to keep it up, in spite of the headaches.

Though IRC can certainly be a valuable service, we think it is generally less valuable than E-mail is, and in our experience, it generates at least as many administrative headaches as E-mail does. We just don't see any way that we could stretch our resources far enough to be able to deal with offering free IRC. If we had another computer, another net connection, and a couple full-time equivalents worth of skilled staff time from people who really cared about IRC, we might be able to do it, but as it is, the thought of all that extra work just makes us vaguely queasy. Our plates are pretty full.

So we permit IRC access only to our validated, paying members. That's a small group of people, who tend to be generous and responsible people who cause us very few problems. In fact, very few of them ever use IRC.

Why doesn't Grex support eggdrop?

Eggdrop uses huge amounts of net bandwidth and cpu time. This may not seem obvious at first glance. It would appear that a big bloated mail program like pine, which we do allow, uses much more. But a user runs pine only while he is connected to Grex. Since we only allow about 80 users to be signed on at any given time, we never have to deal with more than 80 pine processes running at a time. But for an eggdrop bot to do it's job of holding a channel open while the user is gone, it would have to run 24 hours a day, seven days a week. If we let all our users run eggdrop we would have 25,000 eggdrops running at any given time. The fact that it runs all the time means that it would add up to using vastly more computer resources than even big, fat, ugly pine. There is no way we could share our computer over 25,000 users if we let users run things like that.

Given the huge demand for eggdrop, if we permitted people to run it from their free Grex accounts, our system would be almost instantly completely overwhelmed with eggdrop bots, and would be unusable for anything else. Having eggdrops running on our system would not contribute to our on-line community at all, and it does not seem to be such a basic service that we need to offer it to everyone in the world for free. Since eggdrop does not particularly serve our mission, we can not justify allowing its use on Grex, even for users who help us out by donating money.

Why doesn't Grex support bouncers?

Bouncers share the same basic problem that IRC bots have: they need to run continuously. This is one stroke against them.

Grex is trying to provide valuable services to people, and the social value of bouncers is somewhat questionable. It would be easy to say that anyone trying to hide their identity is trying to escape the consequences of their actions, and is thus immoral scum. But we shouldn't forget that a person speaking out against the immoral actions of their government might also want a way to do so without paying the consequences their government deals out to such people. In many cases, a degree of anonymity is a boon to free speech. That is why we allow people to take out accounts on our system without having to be validated. Our primary purpose is to be a conferencing system, and we don't want to put any obstacles in the way of speaking freely in our forums. It is true that a small fraction of our users try to use this anonymity to do harm to our system or to attack other people, but within the limits of our own system, we have chosen to put up with that as the price of allowing other people some legitimate anonymity.

However, we cannot make the same decision for the rest of the systems on the internet. If we want to unleash anonymous people on our own system, that's our right. Allowing people to use our system to gain anonymous access to other people's systems is a far more dubious enterprise. We suspect that if we did so, it would be used far more for ill purposes than for good ones.

Of course, the most common reason people want bouncers is to prevent other users from knocking them off the net by launching denial of service attacks against their machines. With a bouncer on Grex, the attack would be directed against Grex instead. No thanks.

How can I convince you to change your minds?

Grex runs as a democracy. All policies are ultimately determined by the members with public discussions in the Grex Co-op Conference. If you think you can convince our members that you should be able to run a free IRC client, eggdrop, or a bouncer here, you are welcome to try. I don't think your chances of success are good though - this is not a new issue.

What if I just install the program myself?

Every week, we have three or four users try to compile and install eggdrop or BitchX on Grex, and several dozen trying to install bouncers. None have ever succeeded. Here's why:

FTP transfers of programs as large as eggdrop or BitchX slow down our net connection badly. When staff members notice the net connection is slow they look for the cause, and if they see it is an eggdrop ftp, they kill it.
Compiling eggdrop or BitchX on a system as slow as Grex takes a long time (maybe a hour) and slows the system noticably all that time. Staff members tend to notice and kill it.
Once you have your client, bot or bouncer compiled, you'll find that it won't work. We have modified our kernel to prevent non-members from making most kinds of outbound internet connections, including all IRC connections. This is what stops everyone cold. For information (with source) about the Grex kernel blocks, see our technical notes on kernel blocks.
If you got past that (nobody ever has), you'd still have to get past the robocop daemon that kills all background processes not associated with a logged in user. This means that your eggdrop or bounce process will be automatically killed shortly after you log off of Grex.
And if you got past that, you'd still have the fact that we banned these things because running them slows down the system too much. So the staff would presumably notice if you somehow miraculously got the thing to work here.

Normally, we wouldn't mind very much if you wanted to waste your time in any activity as futile and hopeless as trying to install eggdrop or an IRC client on Grex, but we get far too many people doing this and futile attempts to build eggdrop are consuming a significant fraction of our scarce resources. So please don't even try. Bouncer programs, on the other hand, are usually quite small, so you can build those all you like, and we won't even care unless you somehow get it working, in which case we will break it.

Do you know of anyplace where I can run eggdrop?

If there was a public access system anywhere on the internet that was deranged enough to allow random strangers to run eggdrop, we'd be delighted to direct you there, but we've never heard of such a place. We've seen a couple systems try, but they all gave it up within a week. If you want to find a place to run eggdrop, you'll either need to pay money for the privilege (there is a list of places where you can run eggdrop for a small fee here), set up your own system (also likely to cost money), or exercise some inside connections.

So what good is a shell account if you can't run eggdrop or bouncers?

Yes, this is really is a frequently asked question. These days it seems that most people looking for "Unix shell accounts" know only that it is something you need to run eggdrop, and haven't the faintest idea what it is.

A "shell" is is the Unix name for a program whose primary purpose is to let a user run other programs. It's the interface that you use to tell the computer what to do. It normally starts up automatically as soon as you sign on to the computer. If some heathen ported "Microsoft Windows" or the MSDOS "Command.com" program to Unix, then we'd probably call them shells. Most Unix shells work by typing commands, but we have some menu based ones that are easier for people new to Unix to use. The best known Unix shells are "csh" and "sh", but there are dozens of different ones around, including some restricted shells that let you do only a few things. Grex's shells are unrestricted, but our network connection is restricted.

Having a shell account generally means that you have the access to do all sorts of things, not just a limited list. We give out shell accounts because we believe in giving away lots of access.

So what good is a shell account? I dunno. What good is a computer? Grex offers a very large number of services, a few of which are accessible through the web, but most of which are accessible only through our shell accounts. Please do enjoy using the services we provide, and good luck finding a server for your IRC bot.

Document History:

Mar 9, 1998: Jan Wolter (janc) - Initial revision.
Aug 5, 1998: Steve Weiss (srw) - Increased users to 25,000.
Feb 4, 1999: Jan Wolter (janc) - Replaced references to "kill_orphans" with "robocop".
Feb 16, 1999: Jan Wolter (janc) - Broaden discussion to talk more about IRC clients and bouncers too.

$Id: eggdrop.xhtml 1607 2017-05-31 16:16:21Z cross $ We welcome your feedback.

Grex Staff Notes: Security Goals

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

[index]

The security problems on Grex are a little different than those other systems have to deal with. On most systems, the first layer of security is preventing unauthorized people from logging in to the computer. But the whole point of Grex is to give away free accounts to total strangers. We want unauthorized people to log into our system.

From a security standpoint, this is both a blessing and a curse. On the positive side, we don't have to worry about mysterious people somehow logging into our system, because that happens all the time anyway. Some things that are considered secret on other systems aren't secret here.

For example, on most Unix systems, the login program responds to all errors with the message "Login incorrect". They don't differentiate between a bad login name or a bad password for a perfectly good login name, because they don't want to give hackers any clue about which login names exist. But Grex's login program has been modified to give messages like "Password Incorrect" and "No Such Login". Since anyone can get on our system, the full list of login names is no secret. Making the messages more helpful means staff gets fewer requests for help and the requests we get are less confused.

On the negative side, we don't have that first layer of security that other systems do, and we do still have things we need to keep secure. To understand our approach to security, it is important to first understand what our goals are. We need security for several reasons:

Protecting the privacy of users.

Our users should feel reasonably confident their mail and their files are not being read by other people. They should also know that other people can't log into their accounts and pretend to be them. To ensure this, we need to do our best to protect the security of the passwords, and of the root account (which has access to everything).

Restricting net access.

We are happy to give people anonymous access to our system, and we are prepared to deal with having mysterious people doing mysterious things on our system, but most of the rest of the Internet doesn't feel this way. Because of this, we allow anonymous people to come into Grex from the net, but we restrict who can go out to the net from Grex. This discourages people from using Grex as an anonymizer while attacking other systems. Having those restrictions means we must enforce them. This is done on Grex through modifications of the Unix kernel.

Prevent resource hogging.

Grex has very limited resources spread over an awful lot of people. One user hogging a disproportionate amount of our net bandwidth or CPU can prevent hundreds of other users from using Grex at all. Unfortunately, technical fixes to these kinds of problems usually cost too much in overall system performance, or in limiting legitimate use of the system to be desirable. In most cases, we deal with such problems on a case-by-case basis, often simply by talking to people instead of installing technical fixes. For example, we don't use the disk quota systems built into SunOS because they slow down the system too much. Instead we manually send mail to people asking them to reduce their usage, and manually reduce disk space for any users who aren't cooperative. However, when dealing with things manually becomes too much of a burden on our limited staff time, we do install hard resource limits, notably we (mainly Marcus Watts) have modified our mail software to limit the sizes of mailboxes.

Prevent harassment of users.

Occasionally one user will decide that he or she needs to interfere with another user's use of Grex, perhaps by flooding their screens with messages or otherwise messing things up for them. This kind of behavior is never welcome on Grex, and we believe in providing people with tools that allow them to shut out unwelcome messages. The standard Unix messaging programs "write" and "talk" have been modified here to limit abuse.

Tracking problem users.

From time to time we have users who come in and "try the locks," that is, attempt to break our security. We consider such people rather puzzling. Many of them pretend to be some kind of "information freedom fighters," but the only secrets on Grex are the personal mail and files of our users. Taking advantage of the free access we give away to try to pry into the private business of other users, sneak into other systems on the net, or harass people is downright rude. So we like to be able to track such rude people and turn them in to the proper authorities for suitable chastisement. That means we log everything, monitor the logs continually, and keep the logs for a long, long time. If you want to "test the locks" purely to satisfy your own curiosity, please do send mail to help@grex.org first, and please do advise us if you notice any problems. Thanks.

Grex's staff operates with a certain amount of secrecy. Staff meetings, unlike board meetings, are not open to the public. The staff conference is the only closed conference on Grex. This is done for several reasons. First, we sometimes have to discuss the activities of individual users who may be causing problems of the sort described above. We don't want to discuss people's usage in public, particularly if they turn out to be engaged only in innocent activities. Second, there is usually some time lag between the time we discover a security problem and the time we fix it. We'd like to keep the existance of problems secret for that time period, if possible.

In general, however, we do not believe in keeping our security arrangements secret. This is why we have published detailed descriptions of most of our security arrangements on the web. We also maintain a public discussion forum on technical issues related to the operation of Grex in the garage conference. As a general principle, security by obscurity is generally very poor security. People who want to crack your security to steal things are often highly motivated, and secrets will leak out. By publishing our methods, we put nice people who are merely interested in security systems on an equal footing with the bandits. The nice people will probably let us know if they notice any weaknesses. The bandits probably won't. Thus publishing our security arrangements should make them more secure in the long run.

Grex runs SunOS 4.1.4, but has made many modifications to the basic software. Other technical notes give more detailed information about security-related aspects of these modifications to Grex:

The Password Database - description of how passwords are stored and accessed.
The Kernel Blocks - descriptions of kernel modifications to restrict outgoing net access.

Document History:

Mar 30, 1998: Jan Wolter (janc) - Minor updates and corrections.
Nov 19, 1997: Jan Wolter (janc) - Expansion of discussion of secrecy.
Aug 13, 1997: Jan Wolter (janc) - Initial Revision.

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

Grex Staff Notes: The Password Database

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

[index]

This document describes Grex's password database. A good password database is a key to maintaining good security on a public access system. For more information, see our technical note on Grex Security Goals.

We will describe our password database in a historical manner, starting by telling about the standard Unix password database that came with SunOS 4.1.4, then describing the JFH shadow package that we replaced it with, and finally describing our own modifications to that package.

Standard Unix Password Database

All Unix systems have a file named /etc/passwd which contains one line of information about each user. A typical passwd file name from a standard Unix system looks like this:

   janc:DIBU7epiSd4xs:2386:10:Jan Wolter:/a/j/a/janc:/bin/csh
  

This contains seven fields, separated by colons:

name - the user's login name.
passwd - An encrypted version of the user's password.
uid - The user's user id number (a unique number used by Unix to identify users).
gid - The user's group id number (on Grex, 10 is staff, and 50 and 51 are regular users).
gecos - This normally contains the user's full name, possibly with office number, home phone and office phone given after it. It's called "gecos" for weird historical reasons.
dir - This is the full path of the user's home directory.
shell - This is the full path of the user's login shell program.

Note that actual passwords are never stored anywhere. Only an encrypted copy of the password is stored. When you type in your password the login program encrypts whatever you typed in, and compares the resulting string to the one stored in the passwd file. If they match, you must have typed in the correct password. If they don't, you didn't.

Passwords are encrypted using a version of the US National Bureau of Standard's DES (Data Encryption Standard) algorithm. The Unix password encryption algorithm takes the lowest 7 bits of each of the first 8 characters of your password to construct a 56-bit key which is used to repeatedly encrypt a constant string (usually a string of all zeros) into a 14 character string like the one in the example above.

The first two characters of the encrypted password aren't really part of the encryption. They are a randomly selected "salt" which is different for each user and is used to permute the algorithm in small ways, resulting in the encrypted password that is stored as the other twelve characters. Thus, if two different users set their password to the same thing, you won't be able to tell because with different salt, their entire encrypted passwords will be different.

The /etc/passwd file, which normally contain these encrypted passwords, is always publicly readable on Unix systems, so any user can see any other user's encrypted password. Back in the seventies this wasn't a real problem. Knowing someone's encrypted password couldn't get you access to their account, and decrypting a password was simply too hard. However, computers have gotten much, much faster, and there exist programs these days that can do a pretty decent job of cracking passwords these days. With 56-bit keys, there are 2**56 or 72,057,594,037,927,936 different possible passwords. Modern parallel computers can search that in reasonable amounts of time, and widely available programs like crack can do a pretty good job of searching the portion of that key space usually used by humans - mostly words and names. (That's why Grex's password programs are pretty picky about encouraging "non-obvious" passwords - it lengthens the list crackers have to search.)

The other problem with the traditional Unix password system is one of access time. The original designers of Unix didn't expect Unix systems with tens of thousands of users. Grex has about 25,000 accounts, which means that the passwd file is about 25,000 lines long. Every time the system needs to know any of the information stored in there, it has to search that huge file. This can be very slow.

Newer versions of Unix deal with both of these problems. Encrypted passwords are no longer stored in /etc/passwd, though all the other information will still be there, and there may be an alternate hashed password database that can be searched much more efficiently. Unfortunately, Grex runs SunOS 4.1, which is not a newer version of Unix and doesn't support do either of these things. So we had to fix it.

The JFH Password Database

Many years ago Grex's staff (mainly Greg Cronau) replaced the SunOS password system with a public domain system developed by Julianne F. Haugh. The JFH password system does two things that we badly needed.

First, encrypted passwords are no longer stored in /etc/passwd. If you look at that file, you will see that the lines look like:

   janc:x:2386:10:Jan Wolter:/a/j/a/janc:/bin/csh
  

Here the encrypted password has been replaced by an x. (Some Unix systems put fake passwords here instead of an x, but we don't want to encourage hopeful hackers to download the whole useless /etc/passwd file over our overburdened internet connection - though plenty of people try it anyway. Duh.) The actual encrypted passwords are stored in a different file, called /etc/shadow, which, unlike /etc/passwd, is not readable. If you could read it, you would see that it contains lines that look like this:

   janc:ytx9yoTz0xTiYv3eIkk9XOpF:10008:0:365:30:::
  

The fields are:

name - the user's login name.
passwd - the user's encrypted password.
lastchange - The date the user's password was last changed (given as number of days since Jan 1, 1970).
min - The minimum number of days after a change that you have to wait to change it again (zero for all users on Grex).
max - The maximum number of days a user may go without changing a password before the system forces a password change (365 for most users on Grex).
warn - The number of days before password expiration that the user is warned (30 days for all users on Grex).
inactive - The number of days after password expiration until the account is considered inactive and is expired (not used on Grex).
expire - The date on which an account expires (not used on Grex).

Obviously this does more for us than just hide the encrypted password. It gives us mechanisms to force users to change their password from time to time and do other handy things. But hiding the password is the main goal.

The alert reader will have noticed another difference. In the sample shadow line above, the encrypted password is 26 characters long, rather than the standard 14. You guessed it - there have been changes to the password encryption algorithm.

As we mentioned, the DES algorithm uses a 56 bit key, constructed by taking 7 bits from the first 8 characters of your password. But what happens if your password is longer than 8 characters? On standard Unix systems, the extra characters aren't used. That's a waste of perfectly good password.

So in the JFH system, if your password is more than 8 characters long, the next eight characters are also encrypted by the same algorithm. So the result is 2 bytes of salt, 12 bytes encrypted from the first 8 characters of your password, and 12 more bytes encrypted from the rest of your password with the same salt. String them all together and you have 26 bytes of encrypted password, like the sample above.

The JFH password system also addresses the speed question. In addition to the the standard /etc/passwd file, there are the /etc/passwd.pag and /etc/passwd.dir files. These contain exactly the same data as the /etc/passwd file, and, in fact, are generated from the /etc/passwd file, but they comprise a hashed database, which can be searched very rapidly. (To search a hashed file, you take what you are searching for, in this case the name "janc", and use some fixed algorithm to turn it into a number (e.g., you might add up all the letters). Then you use this number to index straight into the database to find the object you want. This can be very fast, but requires that the database be properly structured to make it work.) There are similar /etc/shadow.pag and /etc/shadow.dir files to enable fast searching of the shadow database.

The catch, of course, is that none of the Unix programs that come with SunOS know that the hashed database exists. We have rebuilt the most commonly used programs to use the hashed database for password file lookups, but some programs still search straight through the flat /etc/passwd file. In most cases, this is just a matter of recompiling them with the -lshadow flag on the compile command to link in the shadow library, which includes new versions of the getpwnam() and getpwuid() calls that use the hashed database.

Some programs we don't have source for. For example, the csh we are running is the original SunOS version, which doesn't know about the hashed password database. So when you do "cd ~janc" in csh it is likely to be very slow, but if you do the same thing in tcsh, which we were able to recompile, it is very fast.

Grex's Password Database

The JFH shadow system had several problems, so over the years the Grex staff (mainly Marcus Watts) has been making changes to it. There have been a number of small bug fixes, and two more significant changes.

The first change was related to the maintenance of the hash files. In the JFH shadow system, and in many other Unix versions with a hashed password database, the entire hash file has to be rebuilt every time there is any change. If your password file is big enough to need a hashed database, then rebuilding that database is going to be a slow process. So while the hash system makes accesses very fast, updates become very slow.

The general presumption is that it doesn't matter so much because updates are rare. You only need to rebuild the hash files when you create or delete an account, or when there is a change to a user's name, password, or login shell. However, on Grex we typically have over a hundred new accounts created through the newuser program every day. With Grex as slow as it was at that time, it could take as long as fifteen minutes to do each rebuild, and only one can be running at a time, so it could take about 25 hours a day to do all the account creations. (These days our computer is much faster, but we now have over 200 accounts created per day, so it's still nice to be fast). This is definitely a problem.

The solution, of course, is not to rebuild the entire database every time one thing changes. Instead, you modify the existing database to make only the necessary changes. This is much, much faster, but difficult to do correctly. Marcus has developed versions of the newuser, passwd, chsh and chfn commands that do this, as well as a program to allow staff members to modify, create and destroy accounts.

The other change we have made is to the password encryption algorithm. The method used by the JFH software to handle long passwords isn't really all that good. Those 26-character long encryptions aren't as formidable as they look. Though many users have passwords longer than 8 characters, they usually aren't more than a few characters longer. That means the second half of the password is usually an encryption of a one, two, or three-character long string. It's really easy to crack passwords that short, so you could probably crack most of the second halves of the passwords in a few minutes. Then you just half to crack the first halves as usual. Plus those few letters you got from the second half might help you guess the first half (e.g., if the second half the password of the user "satanboy" is "66" then you might guess that the first half is a seven letter word followed by a "6" - a program could try all those in a minute or two).

This isn't really that big a problem for Grex. After all, since the encrypted passwords are in a file readable only to root, we don't expect many people to ever see them. People can still try to guess passwords without having access to the encrypted strings. All they have to do is try their guesses at Grex's login prompt. But then they can't attack long passwords half at a time (so, in fact, passwords longer than eight characters are a lot more secure), and they can't run huge numbers of guesses very fast because, well, they'd be on Grex and Grex isn't fast.

But there was another reason we wanted to change the password encryption algorithm. Currently Grex is all one computer, but in the future we hope to use different machines for different services, for example, there might be a separate machine to handle E-mail. In such an environment, we'd want users' accounts to work on multiple machines. That means we'd need to use some form of distributed password system, like Kerberos. In such system, encrypted passwords can't stay stored safely away in a protected file on one machine. They have to be passed among machines, and as soon as they start wandering the net, the risks of someone getting a copy of one becomes much larger. We will need a more secure encryption method.

So Marcus Watts formulated the following requirements for a new encryption algorithm:

Long passwords should be allowed, and all their characters (up to at least 128 characters) should be significant.
All bits of the encrypted password should depend on all bits of the cleartext input.
The salt should be based on some combination of the user's loginid and hostname, rather than being randomly generated as in DES password encryption. This is a signficant advantage in a Kerberos-like environment.
We should not use an algorithm which, for legal reasons, cannot be exported from the USA. Thus DES is not acceptable, but md5 or sha-1 is.
The algorithm should return a binary number that is then convertible into a fixed length ascii string suitable for inclusion in a Unix password file. The number should have as many bits as possible, while the string should be as short as possible.
The code should be fast. Many encryption algorithms are deliberately slow, to slow down people who attack the password by trying every word in the dictionary. But Grex is already so slow that we can't afford a password encryption algorithm that further slows down the machine.
It should be difficult or impossible to derive the cleartext password from the encrypted password using any method short of a brute force dictionary attack.

To replace the DES encryption, Marcus Watts has developed a new encryption algorithm based on the SHA (Secure Encryption Algorithm). The one tricky part in this is that password lengths vary, and SHA requires wants a constant length input. So the basic algorithm is:

Concatinate together the following:

128 minus <password length> pad characters (all backslashes)
the clear text password (truncated to 128 characters if it is longer)
the user's name long
the instance (currently always a null string)
the realm (the name of the local host)

Apply the SHS hashing function to the resulting string.
Concatinate together the following:

the clear text password (again)
128 minus <password length> pad characters (all less-than signs)
the result of the previous SHS hash.

Apply the SHS hashing function to the resulting string to get a 20-byte binary string.
Convert the binary string into a string of 26 printable characters.
Prepend the characters %! onto the string to make a 28 character string. This marks it as a result of this algorithm.

The reason for tagging the passwords generated by this algorithm with a %! sequence is that, for a while at least, the password file will contain a mixture of DES passwords and new passwords, and we need to be able to distinguish them. The reason for this is to smooth the transition from the old encryption to the new encryption. We can't easily convert existing passwords from the old scheme to the new scheme. You'd have to decrypt the old passwords before you could re-encrypt them with the new scheme. It's doubtful whether such a project could be considered practical or ethical.

So we are making the change gradually. For people with DES passwords, the lines in the /etc/shadow file look like the example above. For people with new passwords, the encryption string always starts with the three characters %!, like this:

   janc:%!!@Tpf4)X^Pes@Xms8tq(M).U+#:10008:0:365:30:::
  

If the login program doesn't see the %!! in your encrypted password, it uses the DES encryption algorithm, if it does, it uses the new algorithm. All new accounts are now being created using the new encryption, and whenever an older user makes a password change, the password encryption is changed over to the new algorithm. So within a year (since passwords expire after a year), all Grex users will be using the new algorithm, and we will be ready to change over to a distributed password system.

Marcus's actual source for the kg_pwhash() routine that does the encryption is available on a separate page.

Document History:

Aug 13, 1997: Jan Wolter (janc) - Initial revision.
Aug 20, 1997: Jan Wolter (janc) - Various corrections from Valerie Mates (valerie), Scott Helmke (scott), and Marcus Wattts (mdw).
Mar 30, 1998: Jan Wolter (janc) - Minor improvements, updates, and corrections.
Feb 16, 1999: Jan Wolter (janc) - Minor improvements, and updates.

$Id: passwd.xhtml 1454 2014-03-26 23:24:04Z kentn $ We welcome your feedback.

Grex Staff Notes: Equipment Wish List

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

[index] This page contains a list of some of the equipment Cyberspace Commuications would like to obtain for Grex. Obviously we'd like, say a Sun Enterprise 10000 server or a Compaq Alphaserver DS20, and maybe a couple T3 connections. (though, come to think of it, I don't think we'd have any idea how to scale our operations to that level). This list, however, is aimed at things that would allow more incremental improvements on our current operations.

There are a separate pages listing our current equipment and describing its configuration. If you are looking to swap stuff, check our list of equipment for sale or swap.

Cyberspace Communications is a registered 501(c)3 tax-exempt corporation. That means that if you are willing to donate any equipment to us, it is tax deductable.

We will probably buy some of this equipment eventually, but since Cyberspace Communications is supported entirely by voluntary donations from our users, we don't exactly have a lot of money to work with. A lot of this stuff we won't be able to obtain until it gets obsolete enough to be sold cheap or given away.

This are in no special order:

4M or 16M 30-pin SIMMs - Our 4/670 system uses 30-pin SIMMs in sets of 16. We've already got 4 sets of 4M SIMMs and a couple spares. We'd like lots more. Even more, we'd like to get some 16M SIMMs.
Sun 501-1901 Memory Expansion Board - This is the memory expansion board for the 4/670. We have one, but some previous owner mangled many of the SIMM sockets, so it takes loving care to get all the SIMMS in and working. One in decent condition would be nice.
110 Volt Power Supplies - We have drive bays and disk bays from a Sun 4/690 system, but they all have 220-volt power supplies, and we haven't any way to get 220-volt power. Interchangable 110-volt power-supplies exist (like the ones in Sun 4/370s or 4/670 chassis). We have one of those. We'd like more.
SCSI Disks - We have lots of full-height 2.1 Gig SCSI disks. Our budget is tight enough that saving a few dollars of in power makes a difference to us, so we'd like to get some disks that use less power per gigabyte of storage.
Modems - We currently have a row of thirteen 14.4bps consumer-grade modems balanced on a shelf. We'd love an industrial grade rack-mount modem bank, of the sort that ISPs are retiring everywhere. Probably we aren't that interested in small numbers of miscellaneous modems - it's hard enough to administer a bank of modems without having lots of different kinds.
Terminal Servers - We aren't all that overwhelmingly happy with our Chase IOLan terminal servers. We'd love to upgrade them.
FDDI or Fast Ethernet Cards - We have one SBus FDDI card. If we had another we could set up one of our 4/670's as an AFS server (assuming we could find appropriate AFS software). Or a pair of SBus Fast Ethernet cards would be just as good.

Document History:

Feb 11, 1999: Jan Wolter (janc) - Initial Version.

Jul 16, 2001: Jan Wolter (janc) - Partial Update.

$Id: wishlist.xhtml 1454 2014-03-26 23:24:04Z kentn $ We welcome your feedback.